<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Ali Haberfield</title>
    <description>I&#39;m a Stockholm-based web developer.   
</description>
    <link>http://alihaberfield.com/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://alihaberfield.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Fri, 01 Dec 2017 14:11:51 +0100</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 01 Dec 2017 14:11:51 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.1.2</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Lead Dev in London</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/leaddev/daisysquirrel.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;A squirrel in a rather confrontational pose, facing the camera with its tail over its head, standing in a field of daisies&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m always excited when I get to go to a tech conference. They’re a nice change of context and medium for the constant task of absorbing new information and keeping track of what’s changing in the field (I program for the web, so “what’s changing” is everything, always). My day-to-day way of doing this is with an infinitely-growing series of browser tabs containing articles &amp;amp; blog posts I might or might not get round to reading. Conferences are a chance to spend some dedicated time listening to people speak eloquently and passionately on their topics, which makes a nice change and often gives new angles of understanding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What made Lead Dev sound so interesting for me was the content, targeted at people who’ve been ‘promoted’ from developer to lead developer or team lead, and are now charged with solving people problems and strategic problems as much as hands-on technical problems. I’m not myself a lead developer or team lead, but I’ve noticed that what I always find most useful in conference talks is the “how did we make this decision, and what were the consequences?” and “how did our team break apart this problem, and then solve it?” stories. “How to use Hot New Library” and “Meet the hot-shot developer of Amazing Thing” talks are fun, but I’m rarely a user of Amazing Thing or in a position to implement Hot New Library (at least not until it’s aged through the hype cycle a bit). Strategy and problem-solving is always helpful (or, as Pat Kua reminded us on day one: “principles will outlast tools”). A whole tech conference focused on just that stuff sounded fantastic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I got to attend Lead Dev through their fantastic scholars scheme, which assigned me a conference regular as a mentor to help orient me and answer any questions I had, and gave me a chance to meet the other scholars as a motivated &amp;amp; highly engaged sub-set of the huge conference crowd. My mentor was lovely, and being part of the scholars group was a wonderful ice-breaker and meant I never lacked for people to reflect on the talks with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A lot of the common themes that echoed between speakers at Lead Dev are things I already believe: empathy and respect are powerful development skills, continuous learning is both essential and challenging, diverse teams are effective teams, and people skills are the hardest and most essential skills of all. Already believing those things in no way reduced the impact of the wisdom that was being shared. I spent two days nodding along, scribbling notes, and in one awkward moment, spilling my tea everywhere because I was so struck by something I heard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Something I noticed was that a lot of the companies and organisations with substantial vendor presence and/or big groups of employees attending the event are ones that have crossed my radar in the last few years, in a good way. These are places that I’ve noticed sponsoring events and programs for underrepresented people in tech, recruiting through community groups like RailsGirls, and places where I know there is &amp;gt;1 woman in the tech and tech management teams. They’re also places that maintain high-quality technical blogs that I refer to often, and open source projects that I use everyday. Compared to the company presence at other conferences I’ve been to, it felt like a slice of the tech community as I wish it always was- open, community-minded and as diverse as reality is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Below are my notes for some of the talks- not all of them, but the ones where I made notes about things that I’d really like to remember. These mostly aren’t direct quotes, they’re my own interpretations &amp;amp; take-aways- &lt;a href=&quot;(http://2017.theleaddeveloper.com/blog/2017-06-12-slides-from-the-lead-developer-uk-2017?utm_source=twitter.com&amp;amp;utm_medium=social&amp;amp;utm_campaign=pre-release)&quot;&gt;you can view the slides here&lt;/a&gt;, and I’ll link to videos once they’re up, too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For another perspective &amp;amp; more detailed notes from these talks, check out Sole’s notes for &lt;a href=&quot;https://soledadpenades.com/2017/06/12/notes-from-the-lead-developer-conference-2017-day-1/&quot;&gt;Day 1&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://soledadpenades.com/2017/06/14/notes-from-the-lead-developer-conference-2017-day-2/&quot;&gt;Day 2&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;https://capgemini.github.io/learning/lead-dev-conference-2017/&quot;&gt;Malcolm Young’s notes&lt;/a&gt; are also a good read.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;some-of-the-talks-day-1&quot;&gt;(Some of the) Talks: Day 1&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/leaddev/geese.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Two adult geese and several goslings eating grass&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The talk that was most timely and valuable for me was &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.twitter.com/mariaguitierrez&quot;&gt;Maria Guitierrez&lt;/a&gt;’s talk about how to structure personal development. I am someone who usually has two dozen browser tabs open, three simultaneous books I’m reading, and an infinite, totally unmanageable list of things I am trying to learn and document at any one time. I’ve been wanting to get better at this, and have collected an also-unmanageably large list of aspirations for how I will do that. “I should write that up in a blog post” is something I often think when I emerge from a bug-hunting code dive with some new knowledge, and then I immediately get distracted by the next thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I found so valuable about Maria’s talk was that the techniques she gave for narrowing the list from an unmanageable infinity to a manageable handful are things I’m pretty sure I can do. The structure she suggests is a full-day annual goal-setting to generate a list of goals, a shorter weekly reflection against the list, and a 5-minute daily reflection on what was learnt today. Limit the content-hosepipe of blog posts, books and podcasts to things that are on the list. A technique she suggested for generating the list is to go through your role description, and do a self-assessment of your level of skill in each area. Focus your energy where it’s needed. The idea that I could (and actually should) put some sort of a boundary on what I am attempting to learn at any given time is both common-sense and a total revelation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Earlier on the first day, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.twitter.com/adrian&quot;&gt;Adrian Howard&lt;/a&gt; described the role of manager as an organisational developer, with the team members being the customers of the organisational product. With a vision of servant leadership (“Be Alfred, not Batman”), he shared some really useful active listening tips: reflecting someone’s own words back at them, for example “Can you tell me more about {thing the person said, in their own words}”, asking for stories rather than bounded and leading questions, and distinguishing in notes between an insight on the part of the listener and an observation from the speaker. His book recommendation (which might go onto a future reading list if I decide that building listening skills is something I should focus on), was “Practical Empathy” by Indi Young.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/anjuan&quot;&gt;Anjuan Simmons&lt;/a&gt; opened with a delightful insight into a development career as a hero’s journey, in which at some point the hero can take on the role of mentor to a new hero. I really recognise this path for myself right now- I’ve been working as a developer for a while now, and am increasingly looking for opportunities to mentor people at an earlier stage, while still looking for mentorship and guidance from people who’ve gone a few more adventure cycles than me. Anjuan spoke about influence and leadership in the spheres of people, code, customers and scheduling, and shared the profound usefulness of preserving dignity at all costs, especially in situations of conflict.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Release cycles for native mobile apps are a whole different beast than for the web, but &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/catehstn&quot;&gt;Cate Huston&lt;/a&gt;’s talk was full of relevant insights for any development sphere. Defining and exploring in-depth what the catastrophic failure would be for any app- if it’s a text app, that’s losing text. If it’s a gaming app, it’s losing points or streaks. Users will never return after a catastrophic failure. All teams need to be able to clearly articulate the company priorities, and multiple teams working on the same product need to have their incentives aligned, or they’ll be driven to undermine each other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Giving and taking feedback is notoriously hard. &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/eacarlson&quot;&gt;Erika Carlson&lt;/a&gt;’s talk encouraged us to think about why it’s so hard- what’s the fear in giving/receiving feedback? What’s underneath the fear? What opportunities can be gained by pushing past the fear? Breaking  feedback up into the categories affirmative, constructive and passive, she reminded us that feedback is a skill, and skills need to be practised or they won’t develop. There was gem in there about kindness versus niceness- a nice person might avoid giving difficult feedback, but a kind person knows it needs to be done, for the good of everybody. We got some good tips on receiving difficult feedback (say thank you, go away to process it, and reflect and respond once the feelings have subsided a little), and how to give it (be collaborative about how &amp;amp; when is best, be specific, name behaviour rather than personal traits, practise out loud).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Day one ended with drinks, snacks, and bonding with some of the other conference scholars about projects, community, and how our heads were spinning from the number and quality of the talks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;some-of-the-talks-day-2&quot;&gt;(Some of the) Talks: Day 2&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/leaddev/binsquirrel.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;A squirrel on top of a bin eating something&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On day two, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/birgitta410&quot;&gt;Birgitta B.&lt;/a&gt;’s talk about Agile Documentation was another one that was exactly the right thing for me to hear at exactly the right time. The importance of common understanding versus the constant decay of out-of-date documentation is a very familiar struggle. She gave a few recommendations for what should be documented: things that everybody on the team should understand about the application, things that don’t change very often, things that turn up often in conversation with people outside the team, and things that are complex, hard to change and that need to be explained repeatedly. Documentation can be a way to find and address code smells- describing a complex problem can be a way of exploring that complexity, and identifying if it needs to be addressed. I was really inspired by some of the paper model kits Birgitta shared, as ways of modeling a system while discussing it, and by the strategy she suggested for documenting architecture decisions using &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/npryce/adr-tools&quot;&gt;ADR-tools&lt;/a&gt;. This was a great talk about how to have “just enough” documentation, created and updated when needed (and not before), made of maps, how-to’s, history and creative sketches.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Continuing the theme somewhat, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/roidrage&quot;&gt;Mathias Meyer&lt;/a&gt; talked about working in diverse distributed teams, and pointed out that written communication &amp;amp; decision-making can also function as accidental documentation. It was cool to see some examples of the principles and tools of open software development that the TravisCI team bake into their incident response, decision-making and team-onboarding, like using Github issues for just about everything (including procurement), and running company culture discussions as both open and opt-in- invitation open, participation invited but not manditory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/saleandro&quot;&gt;Sabrina&lt;/a&gt;’s talk on big rewrites made some valuable points about when to do it: basically, when the cost of not doing it rises to be equal to or greater than the cost of doing it. Explaining when this is to non-technical stakeholders isn’t always easy, so she suggested making the pain of the bloated please-rewrite-me codebase as visible as possible by explaining the impact on feature development time. Before embarking on any big rewrites, hash out the technical approaches with prototypes, and take Fowler’s “strangler” approach to the rewrite for maximum value and flexibility.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As well as the rewrite, there’s always the option of deleting features and code. To know what to delete, Sabrina suggested defining exactly which features support the core value proposition of the product, and flagging everything else to be considered for deletion. As a way to prioritise time, she suggested identifying the current biggest blocker, removing that, and then repeating for as long as necessary or possible. A suggestion that I have written little hearts around in my notebook is that a team can farewell deleted and deprecated features and projects with obituaries or other ceremonies for closure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Picking up the earlier discussion of mentorship and learning, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/carlyhasredhair&quot;&gt;Carly Robinson&lt;/a&gt; spoke from recent experience about mentoring junior developers, and what makes for effective mentorship. Mentorship is a relationship, so solidarity, empathy and fit are important, and it’s one where the goal is for someone to grow within their craft, so craftmanship is also needed. She gave some great structures for discussing expectations, like outlining what is expected in terms of commitment and progress in three, six and twelve months, and sharing how the parties define success for themselves as mentor or mentee. She suggested tracking progress and explicitly acknowledging progress as a way to counteract imposter syndrome, and pointed out that stretch projects need to have a real risk of failure to count as a stretch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/rkoutnik&quot;&gt;Randall Koutnik&lt;/a&gt;’s talk we got an interesting perspective on how to describe career progression for a software developer. Rather than years of experience- a metric that only describes someone’s ability to continue to exist- he argued for a career ladder based on the sophistication of a person’s problem skills. The person with the least experience takes a well-described problem with a well-understood solution, and implements it. Someone with a little more experience can break down a big problem into its implementable parts, and someone with a lot of experience can, with deep understanding of business and software context, go and find problems and set the direction of the solution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/sjenkinson&quot;&gt;Sally Jenkinson&lt;/a&gt; gave us an insight into the journey from working as a developer to working as a strategist. This might happen because of a desire for more responsibility, a scope-creep in someone’s role, or their interest in increased reach and impact. It’s a hard move to make: meetings and responsibilities multiply, it can get lonely, and internal and external ‘maker’ snobbery can make moving to a ‘multiplier’ role identity crisis. Still, she argues that it’s a valuable transition to make, as developers can make excellent strategists, translating between business and development teams and having a solid understanding of estimation and problem decomposition. She encourages using developer skills to build prototypes, and working hard on reducing technical jargon in communication with the use of tools like the “Up-goer 5” text editor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/crystalmhuff&quot;&gt;Crystal Huff&lt;/a&gt; ran through the importance of inclusion and working against bias in hiring practises, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/jillwetzler&quot;&gt;Jill Wetzler&lt;/a&gt; continued this discussion with the importance of retaining and advancing diverse teams. Jill told us that trust as leaders must be earned, and a workplace must be safe to be productive. It’s the job of a leader to develop cultural awareness and cultural competency, and to stay aware of things happening in the world that might impact team members who are different to themselves. If something happens that might impact a team member, she recommends inviting but not forcing conversation about it, and letting the impacted person guide the conversation. Since a lack of constructive feedback can hinder advancement, work on the skill of giving good feedback to someone different to yourself, including practising, and accepting that there might be tears. Using structure to give feedback reduces the likelihood of bias leading to different sorts of feedback for different sorts of people, and she recommends checking feedback both from leadership and peers for bias before delivering it- “Would this feedback be given if this person wasn’t X?”. To counteract the tendency of people to seek proteges and offer sponsorship of people like themselves, actively and intentionally seek out people from underrepresented minorities for advancement opportunities. Work constantly to level up your whole team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The final talk of the second day and the entire conference was another incredibly timely one for me, since I’ve recently done a couple of talks and found them both rewarding and terrifying. &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/lara_hogan&quot;&gt;Lara Hogan&lt;/a&gt;, author of &lt;a href=&quot;https://abookapart.com/products/demystifying-public-speaking&quot;&gt;Demistifying Public Speaking&lt;/a&gt;, gave a delightfully meta talk in which she continually referenced her own use of the techniques that she was explaining as she spoke. She recommended keeping yourself engaged as a speaker, and therefor engaging your audience, by delighting yourself throughout your talk with things you genuinely like. Pictures and jokes should delight rather than distract or potentially offend. Her biggest advice was to practise, and to solicit feedback- this is advice that I’ve heard before, but her suggestions on how to do it were interesting. I liked the idea of recording yourself speaking and sharing that for feedback with a small number of people so that it doesn’t have to happen in real time- this both makes it easier to fit into people’s schedules and might help me get over my shyness in asking people to watch me speak.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She suggests giving your feedback team specific guidance on what you want feedback on, and if your talk might involve Q&amp;amp;A, practising answering bad, hostile or ridiculous questions, as well as comfortably saying “I don’t know”. It’s important to practise continuing through a failure or a fumble, and to make back-ups of slides and notes so that you can recover from technical failures. Power poses are a good way to build energy right before getting onstage, and once a talk has been given it should be celebrated and rewarded with some sort of ritual of achievement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My last note from Lara’s talk is “Buy ‘Demistifying Public Speaking’”, but in fact I was lucky enough to win one of the copies being given away as a conference prize! I got it signed by Lara, and am seriously excited to have a copy on hand as I grit my teeth and put myself forward for more opportunities to teach and talk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the last talk I wound up at the pub with some scholars and a few other conference attendees, trying (and failing) to pick highlights from the two days of talks. As I left there were still crowds of scholars, speakers and other conference-goers filling the pavement outside the pub with their greetings and reflections. Two densely packed days of information just barely beginning to settle in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/leaddev/egyptiangeese.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Two Egyptian geese eating grass near a patch of daisies&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 26 Jun 2017 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://alihaberfield.com/tech/2017/06/26/the-lead-dev.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://alihaberfield.com/tech/2017/06/26/the-lead-dev.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>tech</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Give production terminal sessions a unique background colour</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;About six months after I started my current job, the first one I’ve had that involves regular contact with production servers and live databases, I spotted this great hint-disguised-as-a-cautionary-tale from &lt;a href=&quot;http://twitter.com/honeststatuspage&quot;&gt;@HonestStatusPage&lt;/a&gt;: 
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/terminal_colour/terminal_tweet.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Being positive first, know that our production shells now have a red background for easy visual recognition. Now, about your data...&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before my current job, I’d been working mostly on a freelance basis on mostly front-end-ish projects. My work involved a lot of files, a lot of source control, and only local servers &amp;amp; databases. In my new role, closer to the metal of the production servers, I was living with the quiet haunting fear of mistaking a production terminal session for development or staging, and doing something absent-minded, with &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/gitlabstatus/status/826591961444384768&quot;&gt;catastrophic results&lt;/a&gt;. I was careful, but I still worried.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Obviously, giving each server environment a clear visual cue in the form of a background colour was a great idea to implement BEFORE any disasters occured. I decided to set up an orange background for my staging environment, and a red one for production. It turned out to be straightforward &amp;amp; I’ve been glad for it ever since.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;give-different-environments-their-own-terminal-background-colours&quot;&gt;Give different environments their own Terminal background colours&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1) Create two new profiles in Terminal &amp;gt; Preferences &amp;gt; Profiles by clicking the + button at the bottom of the profile list. Give each one a name and a background colour. I chose “Production” and “Staging”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/terminal_colour/custom_profiles.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Shows the Terminal profile editor with a list of profile names. Arrows point towards the ones named Production and Staging&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2) To use one of your new profiles right away, type &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;tabc profile_name&lt;/code&gt;. &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;tabc Production&lt;/code&gt; should now turn the background of the window red. &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;tabc Staging&lt;/code&gt; should turn it orange. Typing just &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;tabc&lt;/code&gt; will reset it to the default.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But you don’t want to have to do this manually each time you SSH into Production- a better idea is to set this up in an alias you will use to do your logins, so that it’s automatic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;3) Edit &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;~/.bash_profile&lt;/code&gt; to create aliases to set the terminal profile by name, run the usual SSH command for that server, and switch back to the default terminal profile when the session has ended:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;gp&quot;&gt;&amp;gt; &lt;/span&gt;sublime ~/.bash_profile

Add these lines the file: 

&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;alias &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;ssh_staging&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;tabc Staging; ssh secret@secret.staging.com -p 123456; tabc&quot;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;alias &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;ssh_production&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;tabc Production; ssh secret@secret.production.com -p 654321; tabc&quot;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;4) Reload your bash_profile either by typing &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;source ~/.bash_profile&lt;/code&gt; or by closing &amp;amp; reopening the Terminal tab.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;5) Type &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;ssh_staging&lt;/code&gt;: You should now have an orange terminal window. Exit your SSH session. You should be back to your default terminal window colour.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/terminal_colour/echo.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Command prompt shows &#39;echo &amp;quot;I am a distinct colour that is less likely to be mistaken for a local environment&amp;quot;&#39;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m now a whole lot less worried about distracted terminal commands than I once was, because I have a strong visual cue of which environment I’m in.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 07 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://alihaberfield.com/tech/2017/02/07/give-terminal-sessions-a-different-background-color.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://alihaberfield.com/tech/2017/02/07/give-terminal-sessions-a-different-background-color.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>tech</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Notes from the Three Capes Track</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/hike/blade.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Walking out to The Blade&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m sitting on a wooden bench on a verandah on what feels like the edge of the world. The jagged, towering coastline I’ll be walking tomorrow stretches off ahead of me. Behind me, the hut kitchen, and the sounds of handfuls of kids and their parents playing board games. The social side of the walk- being in a group of strangers at the huts at the start and end of each day- is a little tedious. I want to be in this wild and beautiful place with less company, and enjoy it quietly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But out on the track I mostly am alone, and have a lot of time to look at things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just before I sat down to start writing this we saw a pair of sea eagles, recognisable by their huge size and white bellies, come swooping up the side of the cliff we’re perched on, then dive again, off and out of sight. Among the rocks between the verandah and the cliff edge I can see a tiny, brilliantly blue fairy wren hopping about, as adorable and perfectly round as one of the long-tailed tits we exclaim about in Sweden. Every now and then it spots its reflection in the window and flutters angrily up to attack the glass.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We stopped for lunch today at a spot called Jurassic Crack. It was a ledge of rock overlooking a towering, sheer cliff face formed from these startlingly straight columns of a dark rock called Jurassic dolerite. It was pouring rain but we sat for a long time, admiring the view, eating tuna on damp crackers, trying to get photos that would do the whole towering drama of it some justice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not long after that we crossed a huge wind-swept moorland covered in dense, low brush. I stopped periodically to listen to the birds, but it took ages before I managed to spot one. A tiny brown darting thing, which I think i’ve just identified as a ‘striated field wren’ from the field guide to Tasmanian birds that is present at each hut.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bush smells warm and spicy from the rain that’s fallen and the sun that’s come out now. Eucalyptus and tea tree mostly. It was alright to be walking in the rain this morning, except when we were up on the windy, freezing peaks- then it was a little desperate. Down in the forest it was nice, cloudy and gentle after the glaring bright sun of yesterday’s walk from the beach to the first hut.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/hike/boardwalk.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Boardwalk&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the plane from Hobart to Sydney, starting to make my way back home now. The day after I wrote the first part, we walked out to that thin, tall spit of rock called The Blade. We woke up early to catch the sun rising above the thin band of cloud on the horizon. Wedge-tailed eagles (“look for the ‘fingers’ stretching out from the wings”, said the ranger the night before when we asked how to tell the wedge-tails from the sea eagles) soared the cliffs in the weak golden light. We were the first walkers out on the track.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our early start might be the reason why, not far out of camp, we came across an echidna head down in a tree stump, scrabbling for ants right beside the track. It’s a lifetime dream to see one so close and so unbothered by us- neither moving away nor defensively curled, just digging calmly for ants with its spiky blonde bum in the air like we weren’t there at all. We watched it for a long time, and photographed it from all angles, before moving on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bush out across Cape Pillar towards The Blade was dense scrub that gave way to barer, windswept patches, and on the ocean side to a few wonderful sloping wetlands. We saw many snakes, under rocks and just lingering by the track. In the valleys the enormous black cockatoos screeched and soared, and at the edges of the cliffs swallows dived up and down at incredible speeds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On top of the ridge right before the track descended towards The Blade, the winds were truly ferocious. We’d been warned of gale-force, with gusts of 200km an hour, and up there the gusts had a solid, physical shove. Walking over that unprotected ridge- no fences, no railings, just a 300m drop to the ocean- my heart pounded like I was rock climbing or diving or some other terrifying physical sport. I told my sisters and myself that if I got scared, I’d just sit down, to make it harder for the wind to knock me over.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the wind didn’t knock me over, and it grew a little calmer as we walked out onto The Blade. It’s a really incredibly piece of rock, no more than a few meters wide, extending straight up and out of the ocean and growing both taller and narrower towards the end, until you’re scrambling up bare rock with the long drop to the violent ocean visible just to each side of where you’re carefully placing your feet. And yet despite its narrowness and the wind and that dizzying drop, it felt secure enough that I kept choosing to go on and up, seating myself firmly whenever the wind gusted, shuffling from step to step, til I got to the very top. There’s only a few dense, twisted shrubs clinging to the rock up there, and spotted skinks darting in and out of the cracks. I saw one of them snatch a fat fly out of the air right where I was about to put my boot down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I felt like I took photos while I was up there- victory shots to try to capture that momentous grandeur somehow, and the spectacle of all that towering coastline in all directions- but I see now that I have only a few timid, quick shots of it. The truth is I was spooked by the wind and the height, and came quickly back down. The better photos are from the more secure ground back on the cape.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A little way down The Blade we came upon the first other hikers of the day, and gave them our wide-eyed and enthusiastic recommendation that they should try for a The Blade as long as the wind hadn’t picked up. Then we walked up and over the cape, back to the spectacular cliff top hut, and then with our full packs to a forest valley hut further along the trail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/hike/wallaby.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Boardwalk&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Setting off on the last walk of the track, a wallaby eating grass right by then boardwalk  spotted me and bounded off- further up the track, and resumed eating the grass. It looked outraged as I continued to walk up towards it, and bounded off again- about 20m up the track. We kept playing this game until the boardwalk gave way to gravel path, when it bounded off down some wallaby highway in the tall grass.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Beside the track every day we spotted wombat poo, although no wombats. Wombat poo is easy to spot because it’s oddly cubed, and they leave it over and over again in the same spot, preferring rocks and ledges. It’s like a gallery of poo of different vintages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/hike/ferns.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Rainforest and tree ferns&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rainforest we climbed through to the modest peak of Mount Fortescue was some of the eeriest stuff i’ve ever seen. Small hikers among enormous tree-ferns, bright fungi, few birds, lots of leeches. Then over the mountain and back to the coastal scrub down towards Cape Huay. That was a long walk with a lot of stairs, and increasing numbers of unfamiliar faces- day hikers, coming in from our planned end point at Fortescue Bay. They smelled from meters away like perfume and soap.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The walking track out to the point was a narrow cut through the dense scrub, and in places the swallows used it as a runway, rocketing through at head-and-shoulder height with fearless speed and then looping off overhead. More skinks out on the Cape, and loads of fairy wrens. We ate our last hiking lunch out there, and I toasted my birthday with sticky lemon cupcakes I’d carried for 40km in a takeaway container. They were still good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the end of the track the sun had come fully out, and despite the many warnings that it was impossibly cold, the shallow blue water of Fortescue Bay was looking inviting. I figured that after carrying my swimmers for 47km I should probably give it a go. We jumped in, and didn’t regret it. It was probably 16 degrees, and the prettiest body of water I think I’ve ever swum in. Unreal blue over white sand, and dark rocks at the edges to warm up on afterwards. Swimming in Sweden has taught me what’s so very good about that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m finishing this in the departure lounge, Sydney-&amp;gt;Bangkok. I’ve stepped into the bland nowhereness of long-haul flying, and will soon emerge from it into what the weather app tells me will be a grey and frozen Stockholm morning. I bring with me a mild sunburn, a few souvenirs, and a great joy to be homeward-bound.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 28 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://alihaberfield.com/blog/2017/01/28/notes-from-three-capes.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://alihaberfield.com/blog/2017/01/28/notes-from-three-capes.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Eating on the Three Capes Track</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/hike/cliff.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Jurassic dolerite cliffs&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last year, on a trip home to Australia, I sat in a cafe with a friend who had just finished a walk I’d never heard of. “It’s the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.threecapestrack.com.au/&quot;&gt;Three Capes Track&lt;/a&gt;, it’s brand new, and it’s amazing”, she said.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The spectacular nature shots on her phone were convincing, but so was everything she had to say about the less photogenic parts: a well-graded path, comfortable huts, excellent cooking facilities, well-stocked bookshelves, knowledgeable rangers. It sounded like the perfect hike for someone who enjoys beautiful &amp;amp; remote environments, but isn’t looking for an enormous physical &amp;amp; logistical challenge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mid-year, I started planning to do the hike on my next trip back. I rounded up a couple of siblings and got us all booked in for a mid-January departure, finishing on my birthday. None of us are hugely experienced hikers. I’d done one recent 5 day hike in Sweden, and not much else since my teens. My siblings are regular day-hikers, but packing for a multi-dayer was something new.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I planned &amp;amp; prepared food for myself &amp;amp; one sibling (the other preferred to cook for herself). We are both omnivores, and I am currently under gluten-free orders (I still eat oats &amp;amp; am not strict on thickeners/starches/additives). We decided we were comfortable eating pasteurised cheese away from refrigeration for a couple of days.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My packing strategy is zip-lock bags all the way down: huge ones containing lots of medium ones that contain lots of small ones. Each labelled, and representing a discrete meal, snack or object (what few clothes I take also go into zip-lock bags).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was a breakfast bag, with the oats and the coffee sachets. We each carried our own lunch bag. Dinners were broken up into their own labelled zip-lock bags &amp;amp; we shared them between our packs. I didn’t weigh the food component of my bag separately, but my total bag weight at start was 11kg, including water- this was perfectly comfortable to carry, and dropped rapidly as we ate our way through the supplies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For eating, we each carried a camping bowl, a nifty silicon folding cup, a plastic fork and a plastic soup spoon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Food was sourced from Coles, Woolworths and a camping supply store.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;three-capes-track-4-day3-night-gluten-free-hiking-menu&quot;&gt;Three Capes Track 4 day/3 night gluten-free hiking menu&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;**: These are the things I wish I’d brought more of&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;breakfast-coffee--oats&quot;&gt;Breakfast: Coffee &amp;amp; oats&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;2x instant cappuccino sachet each per day. Total: 12 sachets&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Oats for 6 breakfasts&lt;/strong&gt; (all ingredients combined in a zip-loc bag):
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;300g gluten-free oats, blitzed in a blender in an attempt to make them smaller &amp;amp; more “instant”&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;2/3 a cup of milk powder&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;pinch salt&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1/2 cup coconut shreds- not the tiny ones used for baking, the bigger flakes from the health food section&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1/3 cup each sliced &amp;amp; pitted dried dates, apricots &amp;amp; apples&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Planned preparation&lt;/em&gt;: Empty half a cup of mix into a bowl, pour boiling water over, stir for a minute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Better preparation&lt;/em&gt;: Add two servings worth to a saucepan of boiling water, stir over heat for a minute or two until it softens &amp;amp; thickens to a nice porridge consistency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;How was it?&lt;/em&gt;: It was OK, but to be honest trying to make instant oats out of the only gluten-free-labelled oats I could find in Australia, which were big chewy whole grains, was not a great success. Even after a go round the food processor, they didn’t cook through just by adding boiling water. If you’re not stuck in gluten-free land, this breakfast works much better with regular instant oats from the supermarket.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;lunch-tuna--crackers&quot;&gt;Lunch: Tuna &amp;amp; crackers&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1 tin of tuna per person per day. Total: 6 tins of tuna&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1 sachet of Kewpie mayonnaise, pinched from a Sushi Train restaurant, per day. Total: 3 sachets of mayonnaise**&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1 packet of Mary’s Gone Crackers gluten-free seed crackers&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1 packet of regular crackers. Total: 2 packets of crackers&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1 carrot per person per day. Total: 6 carrots&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1 Nutella snack thing per person per day. Total: 6 Nutella things&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1 Mini Babybel cheese per person per day. Total: 6 mini cheeses**&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;How was it?&lt;/em&gt;: It was awesome, except for the time we dropped a full, open can of tuna in a huge puddle of rainwater while perched on the edge of a cliff. Also, smallish whole carrots turn out to be great lunchtime snacks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;dinner-one-chicken-tom-yum-soup&quot;&gt;Dinner One: Chicken Tom Yum Soup&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1 sachet of gourmet instant Tom Yum soup&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1 zip-lock bag containing 1/3 cup coconut milk powder + 1/2 packet of dehydrated peas&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;2x cans of springwater canned chicken, a delight yet unknown in Swedish supermarkets but readily available in Australia&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;2 single-serve bundles of rice vermicelli noodles&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Preparation&lt;/em&gt;: Empty contents of Tom Yum soup sachet &amp;amp; zip-lock bag into a saucepan with a bit of water. Bring to boil. Once peas are looking rehydrated, add vermicelli noodles &amp;amp; boil for a minute or so. Add cans of chicken &amp;amp; serve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;How was it?&lt;/em&gt;: Pretty good. The vermicelli noodles turned out a bit sludgey, and it would definitely have benefited from more vegetables than just peas, but the tom yum soup base &amp;amp; coconut milk were a tasty combo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;dinner-two-beef-pad-thai&quot;&gt;Dinner Two: Beef Pad Thai&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1 sachet of pad thai sauce&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1 zip-lock bag containing 1/2 cup dehydrated peas + 1/2 cup dried shiitake mushrooms&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1/2 packet of freeze-dried ground beef from the camping store- &lt;a href=&quot;http://backcountrycuisine.co.nz/bcc/index.php/archives/226&quot;&gt;like this&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;2 single-serve bundles of rice vermicelli noodles&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Preparation&lt;/em&gt;: Bring a saucepan of water to boil. Pour some over vermicelli noodles in a separate saucepan or bowl to cook. To the remaining hot water, add ground beef &amp;amp; contents of zip-lock bag. Leave until beef &amp;amp; veggies are rehydrated, around 10 minutes. Drain excess water if it hasn’t been absorbed. Drain vermicelli noodles, add to saucepan with meat &amp;amp; veggies, add pad thai sauce.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;How was it?&lt;/em&gt;: Meh. I didn’t road test the pad thai mix before the hike, and I wouldn’t have taken it along if I had. It was kind of bland and sweet. Was also pretty sick of rice vermicelli noodles at this stage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;dinner-three-beef--bean-quinoa-chilli&quot;&gt;Dinner Three: Beef &amp;amp; bean quinoa chilli&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1 packet of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/cooksimple-Natural-Cowboy-Quinoa-Cinnamon/dp/B00ABLM0JM?th=1&quot;&gt;this quinoa &amp;amp; dehydrated bean mix that I found in the gluten-free aisle at Woolworths&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1 sachet of tomato paste&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1/2 packet of freeze-dried ground beef&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Preparation&lt;/em&gt;: Put in saucepan with ground beef 3 cups of water, simmer for about 20 minutes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;How was it?&lt;/em&gt;: It was really, really tasty. It takes longer to cook than I’d like for camping food, which was fine for this particular walk as you’re not carrying gas canisters or trying to cook on a wobbly rock (it might be a good candidate for “add boiling water to insulated container” type cooking). It had some mildly undesireable intestinal consequences in the following days.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;trailmix&quot;&gt;Trailmix&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before I hike, I prepare a small zip-lock bag per day of customised trail-mix. For this hike, each bag contained:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sultanas&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Peanuts, roasted &amp;amp; salted&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Almonds, roasted &amp;amp; unsalted&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cashews, honey-roasted&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Crunchy chickpeas&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Skittles&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Choc-coated sultanas &amp;amp; peanuts&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1 &lt;a href=&quot;http://gingerpeople.com/gin-gin-candies.html&quot;&gt;gin-gin&lt;/a&gt; per day&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;How was it?&lt;/em&gt;: So, so good. Finished the bag every day. Converted one sibling to a total gin-gin fiend, and formed a skittle-based market economy within the group by day 2.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;extras&quot;&gt;Extras&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A wheel of cheap supermarket brie &amp;amp; a handful of crackers for celebrating our arrival at the first hut. This was an excellent idea &amp;amp; one I heartily recommend&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Tea bags, a handful of assorted. Should have brought way more, as long afternoons in the huts really suit a nice cup of tea&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Small zip-lock of milk powder. For the tea, but wound up being combined with Nutella &amp;amp; hot water to make ‘hot chocolate’. Obviously should have brought hot chocolate sachets also&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Half a packet of gluten-free shortbread, to go with the tea&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Six mini cupcakes my friend baked for me, which I saved until my birthday&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A lil 50ml bottle of whisky for toasting the eve of my birthday&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A couple of strips of homemade jerky, a gift from a sibling who wasn’t able to join us&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/hike/wallaby.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Boardwalk&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;cooking--eating-in-australias-fanciest-hiker-huts&quot;&gt;Cooking &amp;amp; eating in Australia’s fanciest hiker huts&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kitchen facilities on the trail are excellent, but it can get crowded, so it’s still a good idea to plan for minimum prep and cooking time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kitchens don’t have knives, so if you’re packing something you need to chop up, bring your own knife.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kitchens do have sinks with running water and drains, spaghetti strainers, vegetable peelers, fry pans, saucepans and many other luxuries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’ll carry out all your own trash (bar what you decide you can reasonably put in the tiny food scrap bins), so take off all extra layers of packaging before you go, and bring trash bags.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because you don’t have to carry a full load of camping gear, there is some delightful scope for carrying luxuries (like wheels of brie, fresh vegetables, and birthday cupcakes). I’d still recommend going for a minimum food weight menu, and make those luxuries count, because the lighter your pack, the happier you’ll be, all the way along.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were days when I carried way more water than it turned out I needed- I really didn’t need 2L for the 5km track on the first day. Knowing that you can refill your water each time you pass a hut, think carefully about how much you really need at a time. The only day I needed my full 2L capacity was on the last day, which is 17km without opportunities to refill.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The gift shop at Port Arthur before you leave has a small selection of specialist hiking food. It’s too expensive &amp;amp; last-minute to plan on using it as your main food supply, but they have some stuff like packets of dehydrated mixed vegetables which would make an excellent addition to a menu.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The track is every bit as thoughtfully produced as my friend had raved about, and it absolutely lives up to the hype of a multi-day hike for people who want to see some of Tasmania’s most stunning wilderness without needing masses of experience and equipment. If I were to do it again, I’d avoid going in the school holidays (the beautiful wooden eco-lodges turn into giant xylophones with the constant thudding of all those little feet on the boardwalks), I’d take my knitting for whiling away the long afternoons in the huts, and I’d do each day’s walks at a much slower pace. It’s a truly spectacular stretch of coastline, and knowing that you’ll have somewhere warm and dry to cook your dinner and sleep at the end of each day, the luxury of taking it easy should be enjoyed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you enjoyed reading this, or have hiking food tips you’d love to share, let me know &lt;a href=&quot;http://twitter.com/alihaberfield&quot;&gt;on Twitter&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 25 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://alihaberfield.com/blog/2017/01/25/walking-the-three-capes.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://alihaberfield.com/blog/2017/01/25/walking-the-three-capes.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>In which I remember the existence of rel=noopener only after I finally go live</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;After six months or so mouldering on my hard drive, I remembered that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;This site exists&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I own this domain name&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;WTF Ali just put it up already.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, let us all rejoice, I did it. And then, I caught this reminder on Twitter just as I was pushing this site live:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; data-lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;TIL target=&amp;quot;_blank&amp;quot; attribute on a link without  rel=&amp;quot;noopener&amp;quot; could allow a phishing attack....&lt;a href=&quot;https://t.co/JmWhaiGLxI&quot;&gt;https://t.co/JmWhaiGLxI&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hashtag/FrontEndDeveloper?src=hash&quot;&gt;#FrontEndDeveloper&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Dana Giordano (@smallspark) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/smallspark/status/768908206395445248&quot;&gt;August 25, 2016&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And oh, oops! I had indeed given those lovely Instagram photos in the footer of my page new window openings with &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;target=_blank&lt;/code&gt;, without doing the necessary cleansing of the opener reference. Without removing the new window’s knowledge of the original window, it would be easy to change the original window to something fraudulent and nefarious. &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;www.alihaberfield.evil-spy-twin.com&lt;/code&gt;, for example, which would look exactly like this but be made to steal your identity rather than showcase my tech opinions and photos of spiders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had something like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-html&quot; data-lang=&quot;html&quot;&gt; 
   &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;a&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;href=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;http://instagram.com/me/my_glorious_photo&quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;target=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;_blank&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
   	Dangerous link :( :(
   &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All I needed to do to fix it up was change it to something like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-html&quot; data-lang=&quot;html&quot;&gt; 
   &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;a&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;href=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;http://instagram.com/me/my_glorious_photo&quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;target=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;_blank&quot;&lt;/span&gt;  &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;rel=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
   	Safer link :) :)
   &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So there you go, closing one particularly glaring and obvious hole in this leaking privacy and security disaster we call the internet is as easy as throwing some extra junk into your markup, which is probably about as free &amp;amp; easy as it gets.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 30 Aug 2016 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://alihaberfield.com/tech/2016/08/30/go-live.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://alihaberfield.com/tech/2016/08/30/go-live.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>tech</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Post Zero</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;With this complete date &amp;amp; timestamp, the post fails to build:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-yaml&quot; data-lang=&quot;yaml&quot;&gt; 
   &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;date&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;pi&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;   &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;2016-04-07 16:35:11&lt;/span&gt; &lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If I remove the timestamp, or if I set the date to yesterday but leave the timestamp intact, it builds as expected. These both build:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-yaml&quot; data-lang=&quot;yaml&quot;&gt; 
  &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;date&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;pi&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;   &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;2016-04-06 16:35:11&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;date&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;pi&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;   &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;2016-04-07&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Curious.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 07 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://alihaberfield.com/tech/2016/04/07/post-zero.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://alihaberfield.com/tech/2016/04/07/post-zero.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>tech</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
